Guide to the Stanford University, Board of Athletic Control, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Board of Athletic Control, records
1916-1954
SC0506
Stanford University. Board of Athletic Control.
1.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer from Dept. of Physical Education, 1965.
Information about Access
None.
HISTORICAL NOTE
The Board of Athletic Control of Stanford University was established in 1916. The nine member Board consisted of students, faculty, and alumni representatives. Their functions included care of athletic facilities, general control and supervision of the competitive and non-competitive athletic and physical training department, recommendations for staff appointments, control of all funds devoted to physical training and athletics for men, and oversight of competitive sports events. The Board was discontinued when the Department of Athletics was organized in 1945.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The records of the Board of Athletic Control consist of minutebooks for 1916 through 1943, and bylaws, contracts, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other miscellaneous records, 1919 through 1954. Contracts include those with University of California at Berkeley regarding football games, 1920-22, and one among Stanford, Berkeley, and University of Southern California regarding standards, 1923. Also of note is a report by Prof. W. B. Wing on the farming and sheep herding operations of the Board (on campus lands) to produce income for athletic events, 1921, much of which was overseen by Sam McDonald.
Access Terms
McDonald, Emanuel B.; Pacific Coast Intercollegiate Athletic Conference..; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Sports.;; University of California, Berkeley. -- General subdivision--Sports.;; Wing, W. P.; College sports--California.; Minutes.; Reports.
Collection Contents
- Bylaws (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Contracts with the University of California, Berkeley, and correspondence between J. Pearce Mitchell and Chaffee E. Hall, attorney, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and miscellaneous records, includes agreement among Stanford, Berkeley and University of Southern California on standards and copies of correspondence between Stanford President Ray Lyman Wilbur and Berkeley President Benjamin I. Wheeler on the athletic situation of 1919, 1917-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and miscellaneous records, includes petitions regarding Block S privileges, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and miscellaneous records, includes audit report, 1940-1954; 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pacific Coast Intercollegiate Athletic Conference, constitution and rules and regulations, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Wing, W.P., "Report on the farm of the Board of Athletic Control, July 7, 1921" (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Minutebook, with index, 1916-1920 (Box 2, Folder NF)
- Minutebook, with index, 1920-January 1933 (Box 2, Folder NF)
- Minutebook, February 1933-May, 1943 (Box 3, Folder NF)
- Minutes, 1917-1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1921-1923 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1924-1927 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Minutes, 1928-1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Minutes, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Minutes, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Minutes, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Minutes, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Minutes, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Minutes, 1941-1943, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographic Negatives - Head Shots, 1950 (Box 5)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2014-061
  - Stanford Stadium Fund campaign letter, subscription blank, stadium plan designed by C. B. Wing, 1921 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)